A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1930-1934
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1930-1934
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.491 I
This collection consists of 10,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by the Office of the President, Pavilion VIII-East Lawn, University of Virginia on 1979 November 15.
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Contents List
- General Files, 1930-1934
  - "A" Miscellaneous (2 folders) (American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Council on Education, minutes; American Field Service Fellowships; American Foundation [American Peace award]; America Philosophical Society; American Shakespeare Foundation; 2 ALS, Sherwood Anderson to Newcomb, author's meeting at U.Va., speaks of possible debate w/ Bertrand Russell) 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Council (Disciplinary measures including false fire alarms, suppression of 'Cavalier', etc.) 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Advertising 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Alderman, E. A. (clippings and lists of pallbearers for his funeral) 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Alderman, E. A. (4 folders) (correspondence re: death of) 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - Alderman, E. A. (2 folders) (replies to invitations to memorial services in honor of) 1930-1934 (Box 2)
  - Alderman, Life of 1930-1934 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Board--General 1930-1934 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Board (2 folders)--Investments 1930-1934 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Board (2 folders)--Minutes 1930-1934 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Board--President's Contingent Fund 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Alumni Board--Treasurer 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Alumni College 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Annual 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Art, Architecture, and Music (Investigation of Architectural School; Changes in Fayerweather; Virginia Players--Luther Greene; loss of etchings; Payne Collection to be kept up; James Minor's Spanish Paintings; Allyn Cox--Cartoons of Greek Subjects; Hammarstrand affair; Musical Study Equipment, Carnegie Corporation; Music needs--Fickensher and Pratt) 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Art, Architecture, and Music--Bayly Museum (correspondence, drawings, and construction) 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Articles on U.VA. (History of Political Science Department; Science Service, Budgets, Research and Personnel in Universities; "The Univ. of Va. in the Life of the Changing South"; "The McIntire School of Commerce"; "Notes on the Development and Work of the School of Sociology since Sept. 1927." "A Survey of the Manuscripts in Va."; "Training of Teachers for Secondary Schools"; "The last 10 years in Biology at the U.Va."; "Dr. Benton to Zehmer--Chemistry";"Institute for Research in Soc. Sci."; "Va. Quarterly Review"; "School of History"; "School of Psych."; "School of Medicine";"Library") 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Association for Higher Education 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Association of American Universities 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy, Department of (S. A. Mitchell's election as Associate of the Royal Astronomical Society; National Academy of Sciences; Accomplishments at the Observatory; Eclipse Expedition) 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Athletics, Department of (1- 2 of 6) 1930-1934 (Box 3)
  - Athletics, Department of (3-6 of 6) 1930-1934 (Box 4)
  - Author's Convention (TLS; DuBose Heyward to Newcomb) 1930-1934 (Box 4)
  - "B" Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Tree planting in memory of G. Washington; Byrd, Harry; Byrd, Richard) 1930-1934 (Box 4)
  - Bayly Scholarships see Tiffany estate 1930-1934 (Box 4)
  - Biblical History and Literature 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Biology--Blandy Farm 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Biology--General 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Biology--Mountain Lake (dedication exercises; historical sketch; annual reports; swimming curriculum) 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Biology- Pantops 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds--(Applications for Superintendent) 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Correspondence with Architects 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Buildings and Grounds (2 folders)--Expenditures 1930-1934 (Box 5)
  - Bursar--(1, 2) Furniture owned by University in President's House; Scholarship to American Academy in Rome) 1930-1934 (Box 6)
  - Bursar--Alderman Library 1930-1934 (Box 6)
  - Bursar--Budget Changes 1930-1934 (Box 6)
  - "C" Miscellaneous (1-2 of 4) (Catlett, George--Woodrow Wilson Birthplace; Chamberlain, Bernard--Wertenbaker and McIntire funerals; Chamber of Commerce, proposed use of Pantops; Unemployment in Charlottesville; markers showing U.Va.; Memoranda re: new residents; Society of Cincinnati medals, awards; Citizens Committee of 1000; Clemmons, Mrs. Harry--Rivanna Garden Club to plant Jefferson Garden) 1930-1934 (Box 6)
  - "C" Miscellaneous (3-4 of 4) 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Chaloner, John Armstrong to Alderman--Opinions on Modern Youth 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Chemistry 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - C. W. A. and W. P. A. 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Clemmons, Harry to Newcomb (transcript of hearings of National Industrial Recovery Administration) 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Commons (audit; need of boiler; sale of tickets) 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Convocations 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Crime Commission 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - "D" Miscellaneous (Dabney, Virginius--articles in Richmond Times Dispatch; Delta Tau Delta) 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Damrosch, Walter to Alderman 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - Dean's Agenda 1930-1934 (Box 7)
  - DuPont Trust 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - "DuPont--Jefferson Correspondence"--edited by Dumas Malone 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - "E" Miscellaneous (Mrs. Edmunds 3 bronzes sent to U.Va.) 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - Economics--Commerce 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - Education (Nursing, Summer School, etc.) 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - Engineering 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - English--Kent School 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - Extension Division (Stone Collection; The Mind in Motion, News Feature) 1930-1934 (Box 8)
  - "F" Miscellaneous (Faculty Promotions; Ford, Henry) 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships (2 folders) (Joanna Davidge--Randall MacIver Scholarship, Life and Purpose; Robert Burns Waddy Scholarship Requirements; Ms. Janie Slaughter Consular Scholarship; Phelps-Stokes Fellowship, Paper based on house-to-house canvass of all Negro houses in ten square miles; Medical Scholarships Awards) 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Fellowship--James Bryce 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Finals (Governor Pollard, speaker; presentation of Lile portrait) 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Forestry (Seward Forest;- description of estate; trees on the grounds) 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Forms 1930-1934 (Box 9)
  - Founder's Day (Gifts, Speakers; John C. Merriam, Edgar Odell Lovett, Hon. Michael MacWhite: portrait of John Taylor Lomax) 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - "G" Miscellaneous (Armistead Churchill Gordon; Frank Graham; Gold Goblet belonging to J. L. Cabell) 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - General Education Board 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - Geological Survey 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - Geology 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - German Scholars--Emergency Committee on Aid of 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - Germanic Languages (general correspondence) 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - Gifts (3 folders) (McIntire Gifts; "Belroi" gavel; portrait of Noah K. Davis; Great Seal of the Confederacy; Pantops; Music Study Material from Carnegie Corporation; Jonathan Bryan bequest) 1930-1934 (Box 10)
  - Governor's Conference 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Governor's Office (10% cut; Dock Anderson case) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Graduate Department (Report on Research; Report on development of department) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - "H" Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Haden, W. D.--Chamber of Commerce Beautification; Hamilton, J. G. deRoulhac--re: Curry papers; Hampton Institute Summer School for coaches; Harrison, Robert L., Copy of Will; Harris Hart, State Committee on Illiteracy; Hubert, Conrad Estate; ALS, Henderson, Archibald; Henderson, Louise re: 1st Professor of National Philosophy; Hibbard, Mrs. Ford--Kearney House for sale; Hind, A. M.; Hitchcock, John; Hollins Endowment--Improvement Fund Campaign; Human Welfare Group) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Higher Education (Hall, Sidney; Burruss, Julian) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - History (General) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - History--Medieval 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - History--Research Professorship in Southern History 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Honor System 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Honor System (Speech by George Eager, Jr.) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - "I" Miscellaneous (Institute of International Education) 1930-1934 (Box 11)
  - Institute for Research in the Social Sciences see Social Sciences, Institute 1930-1934 (Box 12)
  - Institute of Public Affairs (2 folders) (Lady Astor; Nicholas Murray Butler; Topics of Round Table Discussions; Henry L. Stinson, Refusal; newton D. Baker, Refusal; Report of Committee on Education for Citizenship; Meeting of Monroe Centennial memorial Connection; Loan of Peale Portrait of Jefferson; F. D. Roosevelt accepts and then declines; Norman Thomas, Address; Oswald Villard, Address; Will Durant, Address; Frank Londen, address; Josephus Daniels; F. D. Roosevelt) 1930-1934 (Box 12)
  - Invitations (4 folders) 1930-1934 (Box 12)
  - "J" Miscellaneous (Japanese Embassy; Jefferson Hall, repairs; List of Officers; Jett [Bishop] School for Underprivileged Children; Johnson, W. L., Rehabilitation of Miler School; Jones, Chapin) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Jefferson Bust 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Jefferson Memorial Foundation (Fiske Kimball, letters about excavations in garden at Monticello; Photostatic copy of Jefferson letter; Reception in honor of Admiral Byrd) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - "K" Miscellaneous (Kappa Delta Pi; Kappa Sigma; Kearny, Thomas, Lewis Mountain property for sale conditions; Kentucky Students, plan to visit Harlan and Bell Co. Tour; Kentucky, University of, 8th Annual Educational Conference; Kahn Foundation, Nominations needed) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - "L" Miscellaneous (Lancaster, Dabney, McKnight Case; Lane, Ernest--re: full Professor in Math Department; Lamer, Mary--Stratford on the Potomac; Leguia President -re: Peruvian room; Library, Addresses of Booker T. Washington with introduction by Dillard) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Latin 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Law Building--bids 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Law (Requirements for entrance [age]; survey of Criminal Justice in Virginia; List of Books added to Law Library; John Taylor Lomax portrait) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Law--Clark Hall correspondence 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Law--Clark Hall Furnishings (1of 2) 1930-1934 (Box 13)
  - Law--Clark Hall Furnishings (2 of 2) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Law--Teaching Staff 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Lectures (Wednesday Evening Lectures; Scott Buchanan; Lyndon F. Small; Thomas P. Abernethy; Peter van de Kamp; R. K. Gooch; Garrard Glenn; Sir Frederick Whyte; Dr. Rufus Jones; James Stephens; Vachel Lindsay) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Lectures--(Dhan Gopol Mukerji) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Lectures--(Page-Barbour: T. S. Eliot; Albert Jay Nock; Lindsay Rogers) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Lectures--(Richard: James Moffatt; W. F. Albright) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Legal Papers (W. A. Perkins, attorney) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Legislative Program (2 folders) (Statement of urgent needs of U.Va.; Reduction by 10 percent of salaries; Gary-Moffett bill) 1930-1934 (Box 14)
  - Library (2 folders) (Gifts of silver pitcher, tray and goblets; Manuscripts, proposed specifications for a new library building; Jefferson and Washington letters; Coolidge gift of 42 original letters by Martha Jefferson and her descendants; Summer School--Library Science) 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - "M" Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Macedonian Political Organization; McLaughlin, Henry--re: Country Church; Malone, Dumas; Mariner's Museum; Marsh, E. H. -letter enclosing copy of letter from W. Wilson to Solomon B. Griffin; Miller, Hugh Gordon, "Remarks on Radio on Woodrow Wilson") 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - Madison Hall (YMCA; organization; rentals) 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - Mathematics 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McCormick-Goodhart, L. M. (models of McCormick Reapers and Jefferson letters for sale) 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McIntire, Paul Goodloe--General 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McIntire, Paul Goodloe--portrait 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McIntire Concerts--plans for new series 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McIntire Day--petition 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - McIntire Fund 1930-1934 (Box 15)
  - Medical Department 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Chair in Nursing 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Hospital 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department (2 folders)--Monthly Report of Income and Expenses 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Hospital; Nurses' Home 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Hospital; Ward Patient Statistics 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Public Health; Use of Laboratories 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Medical Department--Walter Reed Bust 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Music (see Art, Architecture, and Music) 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - "N" Miscellaneous (2 folders) ( National Association of Publishers Copyrights; National Conference on Mental Hygiene; National Council for Prevention of War--Petition on World Court; National Education Association--Drinking of Youth, Organized Association for Unemployed Teachers, Chicago situation; National Re-creation Association; National World Court; Near-East Relief; Noel Peace Prize; Noell Act) 1930-1934 (Box 17)
  - National Association of State Universities 1930-1934 (Box 17)
  - National Association of State Universities (separated) 1930-1934 (Box 17)
  - Newcomb, J. L. (2 folders)--letters and telegrams of congratulation 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - Newcomb, J. L.--letters of support 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - Norfolk Colleges--Location of Liberal Arts College for Women 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - North Carolina, U. of--Presidency 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - "O" Miscellaneous (Oberlin College Commission on Coordination of Efforts for Peace) 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - "P" Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Page, Kirby Lecture on Disarmament Conference; Pan American Union, Pan American Day, Bolivar room; Pardee, Alfred, Gifts of Charles IV to Indians; Paris, W. F., Gift of a flag to Library of Louvain; Parmelee, A. M., Gift of books; Parrish, H., Narcotic research work; Peace Meetings; Powell, Noble, alderman's Woodrow Wilson; "Progress and Poverty;" Pratt, John L. Public Speaking, engineering Department new building; Prohibition--Officers sent to game; Publications; Public Works) 1930-1934 (Box 18)
  - Phi Beta Kappa 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Philosophy (General) 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Physical Education (Intramural program; faculty swimming) 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Physics (Carter's theory of heating engines; appointments) 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Political Science (Yale University Press) 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Prospective Donors 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Psychology 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Public Speaking 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Publications 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - "Q" Miscellaneous 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Questionnaires 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - "R" Miscellaneous (2 folders) (Rabun Gap, Nacoochie School; Randolph, Agnes' death; Randolph, Bessie; Raskob, John, Democratic Party on Prohibition; Raven Society, Sculptures of Harold Cash; Red Cross, annual meetings, John Barton Payne; Registrar, late grades; Allen students; Reynolds, L. R., Virginia Committee on Interracial Cooperation, Summer School Plans; Robertson, A. Willis; Roosevelt, F. D.; Roosevelt, Sara D.) 1930-1934 (Box 19)
  - Radio, Education by (2 folders)--Plans for Programs 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Recommendations 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Recommendations for President 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Religion (Conference on Education and Race Relations; Church Unity; "World Conference for International Peace thru Religion") 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Research Committee (Virginius Dabney; Drug research; Miller School of Biology; Rating of Southern Universities) 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Rhodes Scholarships and Fellowships (recommendations, reorganizations, etc.) 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Rockefeller Foundation 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Romance Languages 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Romance Languages--Spanish 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - Ryan Scholarships (amounts, legalities) 1930-1934 (Box 20)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (3 folders) (Sachs, Samuel--re: Ella Sachs Plotz Foundation; Carl Schurz Memorial Foundation; Sigma Phi Epsilon, Scholastic standing of fraternities; re: Harold Cooke; State Conservation and Development Commission, Removal order of State Forester, Chapin Jones; Stonde, Edward L.; Stram Pollution Bill; Stuart, William T., portrait of Philip F. DuPont) 1930-1934 (Box 21)
  - Senate--University 1930-1934 (Box 21)
  - Social Sciences (3 folders) (Institute for Research in) 1930-1934 (Box 21)
  - Sociology 1930-1934 (Box 21)
  - Speeches 1930-1934 (Box 21)
  - Stadium 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Statistics (faculty, students) 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Sullivan Foundation Award 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Summer Session 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - "T" Miscellaneous (Tayloe, Bladen T., gift of books; Taylor, E. D., Edgehill Jefferson portrait; Troubetzkoy, Pierre re: loan of paintings for exhibition at Duke; Tunstall, Robert) 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Tax Returns 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Tiffany Estate 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - "U" Miscellaneous (Photography [Underhill]; University of Va. Magazine; short History of U.Va.) 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - University Honor 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - University Houses 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - "V" Miscellaneous (Virginia Agriculture Exposition Station; Virginia Association of prep Schools; Virginia Antiquities; Virginia education Association; V.M.I.; Virginia Players; V.P.I.; Virginia Union University;' Visitors, listed geographically) 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Veterans Hospital 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Virginia Bankers' Association--Research 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review 1930-1934 (Box 22)
  - Visitors--Docket 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - Visitors--General (2 folders) (Presidency; Resolutions pro Newcomb; Faculty vote; Bayly Art Museum; Hospital to be Built; Gifts, Jefferson letters; Appointments; Committees) 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - Visitors--Members of the Board 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - "W" Miscellaneous (4 folders) (Washington and Lee Student Faculty Conference; Washington and Lee Conference on Business Affairs; White, William H., Honorary Degrees; White House Conference on Child health; Women's Temperance Union) 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - West Property 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - White, William H.--Foundation 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - Women, Dean of 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - Women's Building (Campbell's plans, suggested donors) 1930-1934 (Box 23)
  - Women's Liberal Arts College, Fredericksburg, Virginia (3 folders) 1930-1934 (Box 24)
  - Women's Liberal Arts College, Hollins (2 folders) 1930-1934 (Box 24)
  - Woodrow Wilson--film 1930-1934 (Box 24)
  - Woodrow Wilson Foundation 1930-1934 (Box 24)
  - "X-Y-Z" Miscellaneous (Yorktown Sesquicentennial; Young, Howard--Portrait of Virginia Clemm Poe by Sully) 1930-1934 (Box 24)